[SPEAKER_00]: What is the role of silence in Buddhism in the context of speech, internal and mental silence, and the quiet environment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech is beneficial in as much as it is an abstinence from unwholesome types of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, silence would be wholesome to the extent that it's an abstinence from unwholesome types of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: But silence in and of itself can be an action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's isolated from the context of avoiding specific unwholesome actions, then silence could be bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said to those monks who determined to be silent for the whole winter retreat, as a blanket observance, he compared them... he said they were living like cows, living like sheep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the confusion probably arises because... well, noise is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Noise is sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels nicer when it's quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't necessarily mean that you are absolved of your intentions for why you're seeking quietude.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're abstaining from making noise, because making noise is unwholesome, like, for example, idle chatter, like, you know, when you're explicitly, like, you see your intention, you don't just make this kind of guess as like,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to distract myself, which can feel that way in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you actually check.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is my mind trying to escape from something by speaking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is there some internal restlessness that I'm resolving by speaking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you will clearly see that if you decide not to speak, it's going to feel confining.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to feel like this imprisonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that type of speech you don't engage in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that way, you would be inclining towards silence as an abstinence from particular types of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at the same time, you know, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Silence has different implications, or noise has different implications.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's noise of the possibility of other people talking to you, and that can be a disturbance in the sense that, you know, as the Buddha
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility of speaking to other people will be a thorn to samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not because you enter some kind of absorbed state.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's just because, even if it's not unwholesome, the possibility of speaking to other people or the... you feel the threat that somebody could talk to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that has an effect on your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't have the same perspective over yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: When other people are around, then when they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically enter this mode of, like, eh... seeing yourself in light of other people.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, it's not the noise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like that, you know, neutral noises of birds or nature or even cars or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's specifically the noise of people potentially talking to you, people being in the vicinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what can be... that's what can, again, not push you automatically into unwholesome, but
[SPEAKER_01]: In the more refined types of development, when you actually are trying to cultivate samādhi, that could become a threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, even then, you would not be justified in acting out of aversion to the noise, because aversion is one of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't see that as a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be sure that whatever you will do in silence is not samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's generally what people give in to, like the justified sense of righteousness, to have a quiet environment, being annoyed at disturbances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can be sure that then that's not samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're actually heading in that direction,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that you would be disturbed and you would be irritated by the noise.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be just an objective recognition that, you know, oh, I could go deeper with this if this wasn't around.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you would know that for as long as it stays around, I am only walking backwards if I get annoyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... in that sense, that would be much closer to... even if the noise never goes away, eh... you would be far closer to samādhi by having that attitude of bearing the discomfort of noise, than by just trying to get rid of it, eh... out of that justified... which... which would be aversion, like it's in a... it feels unpleasant, and that unpleasantness pushes you into action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to make sure that noise or conversation on your part doesn't happen because of that internal seeking of an escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not even measurable externally, that only you would know by asking yourself, like, how much of a problem would it be for me not to say this?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you feel like suddenly that makes you a prisoner to your own mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's those specific types of speech that you restrain yourself from and that can vary from day to day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, what specific conversations or what specific
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, certain topics are kind of inherently leading you in the direction of idle chatter, which are the topics that the Buddha listed out in many suttas, because they would... even if there is a practical purpose for them, it's like the kind of thing where you could just go on and on, and it has no connection with the practice, and it's kind of... if the mind is seeking external safety,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that it's inherently unwholesome, per se.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... well, first, if it's done for an escape,
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is really the only time you would be putting much effort of your own to dwell on those topics.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's one thing when somebody brings it up and you sort of quickly respond to it, not to be impolite.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when you know that you actually want to have a conversation about this and explore the details of the topic,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's explicitly when it becomes idle chatter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, unless there's a practical reason for it, and it's just like, I'm actually interested in this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to know more about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you should be keeping an eye out for.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, anything else, like, even if it's for dhamma purposes, but you see that it's like, I really want to talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I don't really care what it's about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just happens to be that dhamma is allowable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, I will speak about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be similar with the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you take that
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you realize, I want to speak anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to talk about something, because the pressure is too strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize, okay, dhamma is quote-unquote allowed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you do it because of that same intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not really any different, if you were speaking about kings and clothing and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's serving the same purpose for you internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the the thread that ties it all together.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are your intentions?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, could one say that if one practices silence rightly as an... like silence is a manifestation of you abstaining from speaking out of unwholesome intentions,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when you're not silent, when you're amidst people, or you're talking, it's more like, you said, when you're irritated, it's more like you're going backwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, that's the sign of you going in the wrong direction, you're using silence in the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it's more like you're trying to get rid of something through silence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas when you practice it correctly, it feels more like, if I understood you correctly, like putting things on pause.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... you're not going forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either you're developing through talking to people, nor are you going backward.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just putting it on pause.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you go back in solitude, then you don't feel like irritated or anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just feel like you can pick it up where you left it off, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but it's... it's not really an irritation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your abstinence from
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be catering to some kind of pressure of the five hindrances, even if it's just restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for that reason, you would be silent.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that reason, you would abstain from speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if the abstaining from speaking is the thing that the mind is pressuring you toward, that's what you realize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, that doesn't mean I have to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: I should simply not commit myself to this avoidance of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you will speak the right amount.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't need to worry about it, because clearly in that case then,
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't even that your speech was unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were just... this... or your engagement with the situation was unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you deal with whatever problem or task you had to deal with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, naturally, you already know that your mind is tending, actually, in the opposite direction of avoiding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to worry that you're doing something unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, now, if you went in the opposite direction of, like, oh, well, let me seek out people, because I see that my mind resisted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's actually a sutra where the Buddha says that...
[SPEAKER_01]: It talks about all the jhānas, and then it says, if a monk, then, if his mind inclines towards sitting, any of the four postures, he sits, or he stands, or he walks, and then it even says, if his mind inclines towards speaking, he speaks, or if his mind inclines towards being silent, he will be silent.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it's not automatic, as people might think, that you would always be
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be based on any of the five herencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no like internal impulse forcing you to do either of those.